https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DjTs-rjVkB8 If you're an economist who believes in an active role for the government in managing
Nếu là một nhà kinh tế tin vào vai trò chủ đạo của chính phủ trong việc quản lí nền kinh tế,
the economy, then you know that fiscal policy -- changes in government spending and/or taxation
bạn hiểu rằng chính sách tài chính trong việc chi tiêu hay hệ thống thuế của chính phủ thay đổi
to achieve particular macroeconomic goals -- is one type of tool that you can use. But
nhằm đạt được những mục tiêu kinh tế vĩ mô cụ thể- một công cụ mà bạn có thể sử dụng.
did you know that you can stimulate or slow spending by increasing or decreasing the amount
Nhưng bạn có biết rằng, ta có thể kích thích hay cắt giảm chi tiêu bằng cách tăng hay giảm
of money that's available? By definition, monetary policy is changes to the money supply
lượng tiền có sẵn? Theo định nghĩa, chính sách tiền tệ là những thay đổi đối với  việc cung ứng tiền tệ
in order to achieve particular macroeconomic goals. Unlike fiscal policy, which in the
nhằm đạt được những mục tiêu kinh tế vĩ mô cụ thể. Không giống như chính sách tài chính
case of the US, is jointly driven by Congress and the president, monetary policy in the
bị cho phối bởi Quốc hội và tổng thống, chính sách tiền tệ
US is controlled by our central bank, the Federal Reserve. But more about the Fed in
của Mỹ được kiểm soát bởi ngân hàng trung ương- Cục Dự trữ. Thông tin cụ thể hơn
Episode 31. For right now, if we’re talking about the changing money supply, the first
sẽ có trong phần 31. Bây giờ, nếu chúng ta tiêp tục nói đến việc thay đổi cung ứng tiền tệ,
questions I have are: 1) what exactly is money, and 2) what exactly is the money supply?
Câu hỏi đầu tiên tôi đưa ra là: 1) Tiền tệ là gì? 2) Cung ứng tiền tệ là gì?
By definition, money is any good that is widely accepted for the purposes of exchange, and
Theo định nghĩa, tiền tệ là bất cứ loại hàng hóa nào được chấp nhận rộng rãi với mục đích trao đổi,
in the repayment of debts. Over the years, many items have been used as money -- coins
và thanh thoán nợ. Qua các năm, nhiều vật dụng đã đươc sử dụng như tiền: đồng xu,
and paper, yes, but also shells, furs, cigarettes… as long as the item is widely accepted for
giấy, và cả vỏ sò, lông thú, thuốc lá... miễn là những vật dụng này được chấp nhận rộng rãi
the purposes of exchange, and in the repayment of debts, that item serves as money.
cho mục đích trao đổi, thanh toán nợ thì nó đều có chức năng như là tiền.
To serve well as money, though, there are three basic functions of money that must be
Tuy nhiên, để phục vụ chức năng là tiền tệ, cần phải đáp ứng được 3 chức năng cơ bản của tiền tệ:
fulfilled: 1) money serves as a medium of exchange. Without money we would have to barter
1) tiền là một phương tiện trao đổi. Không có tiền, việc trao đổi hàng hóa,
or trade, and transactions become much more difficult. Oh, barter works fine when there's
buôn bán và giao dịch trở nên khó khăn hơn. Việc trao đổi hàng hóa vẫn diễn ra bình thường
a double coincidence of wants -- you have something I want, and I have something you
khi có nhu cầu trao đổi giữa hai bên: bạn có thứ tôi cần, còn tôi có thứ bạn muốn,
want -- but if we don't, transactions become much more complex. OK, here's an example:
nhưng nếu chúng ta không có thì việc giao dịch sẽ trở nên phức tạp hơn nhiều. Lấy ví dụ như sau:
You want to learn economics, and I can provide that service for you. I want someone to babysit,
Bạn muốn học ngành Kinh tế, tôi có thể cung cấp dịch vụ đó cho bạn. Tôi muốn tìm một người giữ trẻ,
and that’s a service you can provide for me. But what if a student wants to learn economics
và bạn có thể cung cấp dịch vụ đó cho tôi. Nhưng nếu một sinh viên muốn học Kinh tế
from me, and offers me golf lessons in return? I have no interest in golf, so that student
từ tôi và đề nghj đáp lại bằng những bài học đánh golf thì sao ? Tôi không có hứng thú với môn thể thao đó, nên cậu sinh viên đó
will have to find someone else to trade with, then come back and trade with me. If only
sẽ phải tìm một người khác để trao đổi rồi quay lại cới tôi.
we had money, something we would all accept for exchanges -- how much easier this transaction
Nếu có tiền, tất cả chúng ta sẽ chấp nhận trao đổi nhiều thứ- việc giao dịch sẽ
would be!
dễ dàng hơn nhiều!
2) The second function money needs to serve is as a unit of account, i.e. money gives
2) Chức năng thứ hai : tiền là phương tiện thanh toán, tức là tiền
us a common measurement in which values are expressed. For example, what there is no money
là thước đo chung cho các giá trị. Ví dụ, bạn muốn học kinh tế tại trường này nhưng lại không có tiền,
and you want to learn economics at this college. There are multiple instructors; what if one
thì sẽ có rất nhiều người hướng dẫn; chuyện gì xảy ra
wants to be paid in babysitting, another in computer help, and another pet sitting, and
nếu ai đó muốn được trả công trong việc trông trẻ, trợ giúp máy tính, chăm thú cưng...?
so on? It becomes very difficult to tell who has the best price. But if every instructor
Rất khó để chỉ ra người có giá tốt nhất. Nhưng nếu mỗi người hướng dẫn đều
charges in the same item, the accepted money, it becomes very clear who has the lowest price.
muốn đổi lấy cùng một thứ, ở đây là tiền, mọi thứ sẽ rõ ràng về ai có giá trị thấp nhất.
3) The third function that money needs to serve is as a store of value, that is, money
Chức năng thứ 3 của tiền tệ là lưu trữ giá trị, tức là tiền vẫn giữ được
maintains its value over time. This enables saving, lending, and borrowing.
giá trị của mình qua thời gian. Chức năng này bao gồm tiết kiệm, cho vay, mượn.
Do we need to have money? No; an economy could function without money, but transactions would
Chúng ta cần có tiền? Một nền kinh tế không thể hoạt động mà không có tiền, nhưng các giao dịch
be much more cumbersome. Money helps the economy move along more smoothly, reducing transactions
sẽ cồng kềnh hơn nhiều. Tiền tệ giúp nền kinh tế chuyển động nhanh chóng, dễ dàng hơn và
costs.
giảm bớt các chi phí.
Now that we know something about money, what is the definition the money supply, i.e.,
Đó là những vấn đề cơ bản về tiền tệ, còn khái niệm về cung ứng tiền tệ thì sao, tức là
what's included in the money supply? Well, there are actually multiple official versions
cung ứng tiền tệ gồm những gì? Thực tế, có rất nhiều phiên bản chính thức của
of the money supply; let’s start the narrowest definition, M1. M1 includes the components
hệ thống cung ứng tiền tệ. chúng ta sẽ bắt đầu với định nghĩa hẹp nhất, M1. M1 bao gồm
of money that are most easily and immediately converted to goods and services, or the most
of money that are most easily and immediately converted to goods and services, or the most
liquid assets -- currency held outside banks, checkable deposits, and travelers checks.
liquid assets -- currency held outside banks, checkable deposits, and travelers checks.
The M2 money supply is actually the most common definition; it includes everything in M1,
The M2 money supply is actually the most common definition; it includes everything in M1,
plus assets that are slightly more difficult to convert to goods and services, like small
plus assets that are slightly more difficult to convert to goods and services, like small
denomination time deposits (that is, CDs), where you'll pay a penalty for cashing in
denomination time deposits (that is, CDs), where you'll pay a penalty for cashing in
early, or savings deposits, money market accounts, etcetera.
early, or savings deposits, money market accounts, etcetera.
M3, then, includes everything M2, plus longer-term CDs and financial agreements; that is, M3
M3, then, includes everything M2, plus longer-term CDs and financial agreements; that is, M3
contains elements that are more difficult yet to convert to goods and services.
contains elements that are more difficult yet to convert to goods and services.
Understanding what's included in the money supply is important in understanding how the
Understanding what's included in the money supply is important in understanding how the
money supply can actually be controlled, and changed, in order to manipulate the economy.
money supply can actually be controlled, and changed, in order to manipulate the economy.
NEXT TIME: Creating money TRANSCRIPT00(MACRO) EPISODE 29: WHAT IS MONEY?
Bài tiếp theo: Kiếm tiền TRANSCRIPT00(MACRO) EPISODE 29: WHAT IS MONEY?